Okay, בוקר טוב *Boker tov* חודש טוב *Chodesh tov*, we start סדר
טהרות taharot. *Seder Taharos* and מסכת masechet נדה niddah, *Masechet Niddah*. We
will finish טהרות taharas *Taharos* when we finish the מסכת *Masechet*; it's
the only one in טהרות *Taharos* that there is a גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara* on. And the reason is obvious, because there are obviously נדה
niddah *Niddah* is not only a question of טומאה וטהרה tumah vetaharah
*Tumah v'Taharah* in the sort of classic sense, but also has implications
in terms of nowadays what we call טהרת המשפחה *Taharas Hamishpacha*, somewhat
euphemistically, but basically has to do with because there's also the prohibition
of having sex, a man and a woman when the woman is
a נדה niddah, *Niddah* or has the related טומאות *Tumot* which are
also associated, also in the תורה Torah *Torah* compared to טומאת נדה
niddah, *Tumat Niddah*, which is the טומאה tumah *Tumah* of a זבה
*Zavah* or of a יולדת *Yoledet*. So because of that practical implication,
that is why we have an entire מסכת *Masechet* devoted to it.
But that being said, a major part of this מסכת *Masechet* have
nothing to do with the prohibition of sex, or even with the
status of the woman vis-a-vis the prohibition of sex, but have to
do with the just the pure טומאה וטהרה tumah vetaharah *Tumah v'Taharah*
question. Is the woman טמאה tmeiah *Tmeia* for implications of: can she
touch some תרומה terumah *Terumah*? Can she go into the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*? All of those implications that have no relevance
nowadays. So a lot of this מסכת *Masechet* will be dealing with
that, not with the איסור issur *Isur* of sex. And by the
way, you know, we just finished reading this, the whole first appearance
of נדה niddah? *Niddah* is in תזריע *Tazria*,
and there, you know, it just speaks about the טומאה tumah *Tumah*
of the נדה niddah *Niddah*, like the זב *Zav* and the זבה
*Zavah* etc. And it's only really in אחרי מות *Achrei Mos* וקדושים
*v'Kedoshim* that we find out that there's also a prohibition of sex,
and it is really the only טומאה tumah, *Tumah* that has that
associated prohibition of sex. One could also include with that a מצורע
*Metzora*, but it's not really the same. A מצורע *Metzora* sent out
of the מחנה *Machaneh* and it says מחוץ לאהלו *Michutz La'oholo*, so
חז"ל *Chazal* understand that there's a prohibition of sex, but it only
applies to the male מצורע *Metzora*, not to the female one, and
it's certainly not of the same severity. It's not really directly associated
with the טומאה tumah *Tumah* in the same way; it really is
limited to the case of נדה niddah, *Niddah*, which raises a fascinating
question of why.
I won't answer that now, we can be thinking about that as
we're learning the מסכת *Masechet*, but there are these two distinct concepts
that are intertwined. And as I said, a lot of the מסכת
*Masechet* really is not devoted to the הלכתי halachic *halachic*, the relevant
aspects for us today, but just to the aspect of טומאה tumah
*Tumah*. The fascinating question to be asking and thinking about is how
are these two concepts related to one another? And when a woman
is טמאה tmeiah, *Tmeia* for the cases of, let's say, תרומה terumah
*Terumah* and קרבנות *Korbanot* and so on, does that automatically mean that
she is טמאה tmeiah, *Tmeia* for the question, the status of the
prohibition of sex? We assume that those go together; as I said,
the תורה Torah. *Torah* anyway only talks about the איסור *Isur* sex
with a נדה niddah? *Niddah*, does not talk about it with a
זבה *Zavah* or יולדת *Yoledet*. חז"ל *Chazal* understand that it's the same
because it's the same טומאה tumah *Tumah*, the טומאות *Tumot* are related.
But that's an interesting question to be asking, and sometimes we will
find discussions here about certain things that are required for a נדה
niddah *Niddah*, like, you
know, various issues about בדיקות bedikot. *Bedikos*, discussions of כתמים *Kesamim*, a
lot of discussions, and some of the ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim* ask, maybe
this only is in a world of טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah, *Tumah
v'Taharah*, maybe this doesn't apply nowadays when it's just about the prohibition
of sex and not about the world of טומאה וטהרה tumah ve-tahara,
*Tumah v'Taharah*. So those are, that relationship of those two is going
to be an ongoing discussion. Having said that, we now open with
the first משנה Mishna *Mishnah*, which is exactly a discussion about this,
about the woman as a נדה Niddah *Niddah* and the relevance of
her status within the world of טומאה tumah וטהרה *Tumah v'Taharah*, not
relevant for us today when we focus on the prohibition of sex.
Yes, Michael?
You said that a מצורע *Metzora* may have the same prohibition.
It's not the same, it's not איסור כרת issur kares *Isur
Kares*, it's an
איסור לאו *Isur Lave* or מצוה *Mitzvah*, it's one of the ניהוגי
מצורע *Nihugei Metzora*.
When it says וישב מחוץ לאהלו *Vishav Michutz La'oholo*, it doesn't necessarily
mean just literally, let's say the מצורע *Metzora*'s spouse wants to join
them.
Yes, that is why I'm telling you, no, because חז"ל *Chazal* understand
that that's an איסור תשמיש *Isur Tashmish*, but that's just like a
מנהג *Minhag* of the מצורע *Metzora*, it's an עשה *Aseh*, it's not
anywhere near the same category. Okay, so let's take a look at
the first משנה mishnah *Mishnah*. שמאי Shammai אומר *Shammai Omer*, interesting שמאי
Shammai. *Shammai* not בית שמאי Beit Shammai *Beis Shammai*, so this obviously
goes back a good deal. שמאי Shammai *Shammai* says, כל הנשים kol
hanashim, דיין שעתן dayan sha'atan. *Kol Hanashim Dayan Sha'atan*, all women their
hour suffices. What this is relating to is the question that a
woman bleeds, she sees that she has just menstruated, and the question
is, but maybe it happened a while, you know, maybe she started
bleeding a while ago and she didn't see. Now that, how could
that be? Two ways. Number one, maybe she didn't check her underwear,
she didn't see when she started bleeding. Or, and this was a
very important idea within נדה Niddah *Niddah*, is that חז"ל *Chazal* also
understand that
a woman becomes a נדה Niddah, *Niddah* when the blood leaves the
uterus and goes passes through the cervix, but even when it still
is interior within the woman.
So therefore, that is a principle called אשה מטמאה מבפנים metamei mibifnim,
כמבחוץ *Isha Mitama Mabifnim Kimibachutz*. Even on the inside before like the
point when the blood exits the body. If that's true, that leads
to a lot of questions: when exactly did she become a נדה?
Niddah? As everybody knows nowadays in the observance of נדה, there are
a lot of internal checks, בדיקות. None of that would be necessary
if a woman became טמאה temeiah, only once the blood left the
body. Because who needs to check on the inside? You wait till
you see blood on the outside. So this הלכה halacha has profound
implications, and one of them is here. A woman sees that she
has bled. Okay, that's very nice, she's bled now, but when did
it happen first? When did it go from, when did it leave
the uterus, pass the cervix, or maybe when did it come even,
and even if it came out of the body, maybe she didn't
check right away. But even if she checked, when did she begin
the process? So this is the question, and therefore what's the relevance?
Let's say she touched תרומה terumah this morning, and she finds this
afternoon that she had her period. So is that תרומה terumah, טהור
tahor or טמא? tamei? So what do you say? So בית שמאי
Shammai says דיין שעתן. It's enough for them the moment that they
found that they were טמאות, tmeiot, and only from that moment on
are they טמא, tamei, not from, they don't have to be concerned
about any prior time. That is שמאי's Shammai. principle. We'll see this
in the גמרא, Gemara but just to give you two important concepts
what's behind שמאי. Shammai, One is a formal halachic principle of חזקה.
chazakah. She had a חזקה chazakah being טהור, tahor, so we assume
that she remained טהורה tehorah until the last possible moment, until we
found out otherwise. The other is that exactly that question of maybe
she began earlier, שמאי Shammai isn't concerned with that. שמאי Shammai says
we're not so concerned that the blood is going to, you know,
sort of get delayed before coming out of the woman's body. It'll
come out right away, and we don't have to be concerned that
maybe it was, you know, passed through the cervix and still was
in the vaginal canal before coming out of her body. We're not
concerned about that, and those are two principles of שמאי. Shammai The
גמרא Gemara. will talk about both. And therefore he says we are
only worried from the moment the blood is found onwards. Yes, Eli?
Two things. One is if you don't hold like שמאי, Shammai now
if she didn't just touch the תרומה terumah, but eat the תרומה,
terumah let's say she was בת כהן bat kohen or אשת כהן.
eshet kohen. Right. She's committed a very serious sin inadvertently.
Well, בספק, besafek, בשוגג, beshogeg, and you know, and then the question
is it might not have been because she might have been an
אונס. ones. If it was during the time of month that she
was expected to get her period, we'll be discussing this, her עונה,
onah, וסת, vesset, then it's irresponsible to be doing behavior that would
be prohibited. So she shouldn't be having sex, she shouldn't be eating
תרומה, terumah. she's expecting to get her period any minute. But if
it's during the time of month she's not expecting that, then she
has no reason to expect it'll happen, and if it happens and
she wasn't aware, she was an אונס, ones, so it would have
been, yes, it would have been an eating תרומה terumah, בטומאה, betumah,
but it would have been a complete אונס, ones, so there would
not have been a liability there. The question is whether she should
have had reason to anticipate it or not.
And this is an example where שמאי Shammai is more lenient than
הלל. Hillel.
That is correct. This is one of the cases where שמאי Shammai
is מיקל, meikel, yes.
But שמאי Shammai, would agree that if she actually did check internally
and she found blood then she's clearly טמאה, tme'a but why do
we say though, if it's still inside of you, it's still...
Okay, that's one of the, they learn it out from a פסוק,
pasuk, we'll get to it, that she's מטמאה מבפנים, yes, Rivka?
Why does it say כל הנשים, kol hanashim why not just הנשים?
hanashim?
Because we are going to see about different, that there might are
different subcategories like women who are called מסולקות דמים, mesulakot damim, who
normally are where not expecting to, you know, would normally have their
period suspended like pregnant women, nursing women. We'll talk about women that
have a regular time they're expecting their period and so on. So
כל הנשים means regardless of what category she falls in, it's always
the case. הלל Hillel will distinguish between women. So let's take a
look. הלל אומר Hillel omer מפקידה לפקידה, mipkuda lipkuda, from the checking
to the checking, ואפילו ימים הרבה, va'afilu yamim harbeh, even after many
days. So if she checked on Monday and saw she was טהור,
tahor, and then she checked again on Thursday and saw that she
was and saw that she had bled, then every, all the time
between Monday and Thursday, she has to be concerned maybe she actually
bled sometime between those two days, and anything she touched would be
ספק טמא.
safek tamei. Or checked a month ago?
Or checked a month ago. Now, by the way though, once you're
living in a world of טומאה וטהרה as we're going to see,
we're going to find out that women checked twice a day. Okay,
in morning and in the evening, every single day, every day of
the month, not just when they were trying to get their, you
know, go to the מקוה mikvah and become טהור tahor after having
bled. No, because you're always concerned, oh my god, I might be
טמאה, tame'ah, I might have touched תרומה. terumah, So at least according
to some, I mean we'll see, there was a practice of checking
twice a day. So saying since the last time you checked is
a day or a half a day, if you're doing what you're
supposed to be doing. Okay, if you're not doing it, then it
could be a lot of days. But that is, there was a
practice of checking twice a day which we will find out about.
Okay, Rivky, you wanted to say something?
Why would she be touching תרומה, trumah, why was it every woman?
Maybe she's married to a כהן kohen or a בת כהן. bat
kohen. And what if she's not married? Then it's not a problem.
So then, so women not necessarily be כהן, kohen,
then women not married to a כהן kohen
don't have to worry about this. And if they're not going to
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash they're not... right, exactly. Well, that's a
good point, but we don't find that. We find that in a
world of טומאה וטהרה where that was a heightened concern, then even
people that weren't eating תרומה, terumah. A, we know that there was
a practice of eating חולין בטהרה. chullin betaharah. And B, you know,
you might not be a כהן, kohen, but you might be friends
with a כהן, kohen, you know, or בת כהן bas kohen or
wife of a כהן, kohen, and then, you know, you touch her
and then she touches the תרומה, trumah so it's in that type
of a world everybody has to sort of be more aware. But
it does get to be, and the ראשונים Rishonim say this explicitly,
it gets to be quite extreme. Like there's not even so, you
know, like rational how much the level of concern, which is why
when we say, oh, now that we're just dealing with normal איסורים,
issurim, like the איסור כרת of having sex, right? Which is a
pretty weighty thing, but you know, then we can go back to
sort of like more normal level of concerns. So clearly when you're
dealing in a world of טומאה וטהרה, part of what was associated
with that was like extreme levels of concern. But you're right, you
know, her herself she probably wouldn't have to worry, but she could
touch her friend and her friend could touch and so on. Okay,
so הלל Hillel says from the last from checking to checking, ואפילו
ימים הרבה, v'afillu yamim harbeh, even if over a lot of time.
וחכמים אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, the sages say, לא כדברי זה ולא כדברי
זה, lo k'divrei zeh v'lo k'divrei zeh, not like שמאי Shammai. who's
too lenient, not like הלל Hillel who's too strict, אלא ella there's
two things that could limit the time. מעת לעת, me'es l'es, from
time to time meaning within the last 24 hours, ממעטת על יד
מפקידה לפקידה, mema'etes al yad mipkida l'pkida, is limited through the last
checking. רש"י Rashi actually reads it the opposite which is 24 hours
limits the last checking, but I think the grammar works better this
way. ומפקידה לפקידה u'mipkida l'pkida and the and from the last checking
ממעטת על יד מעת לעת mema'etes al yad me'es l'es is limited
by the measure of 24 hours. So it is the lesser of
24 hours and the last checking. Okay, so we don't go say
you don't have to worry anything retroactively, but we're not going to
say more than 24 hours back. So at most 24 hours back
and even that will be less if you checked more early, you
know, since then, because obviously if you checked and you were טהורה,
tehorah, that's obviously that then it didn't happen prior to that time.
So it's either 24 or so the lesser of 24 hours and
the last time you checked.
I have a question. Obviously not dealing with the idea of חזקה,
chazakah, so is it a are they talking about what they think
is reality?
Yeah,
it seems so. Right, so so Dov makes an excellent point which
is הלל ושמאי Hillel v'Shammai you could explain in formalistic ways. שמאי
Shammai, just says she has a חזקת טהרה, chezkas taharah, she remains
טהורה tehorah until we know otherwise. הלל Hillel says now she's טמאה,
tame'ah, so we apply that status retroactively until we knew definitely otherwise
in the entire gap. Where's 24 hours come from? That's not a
formalistic rule. So yes, it is based more on a מציאות, metzius,
on a reality, the unlikelihood that she would have bled more than
24 hours ago and not have been aware of it. So we
will see about that in the גמרא.
Gemara My question is is it based on the do you think
it's based on reality their perception of reality or is it arbitrary?
Oh, we have to make some we have to make some limit,
24 hours is a reasonable amount of time. That's a good question.
Let's see how the גמרא Gemara conceptualizes it, but you're right. Meaning
the whole thing here anyway could be meaning the גמרא Gemara. makes
it clear that even according to הלל, Hillel, all this retroactive concern
is rabbinic, so once the whole concern retroactively is rabbinic, maybe we
could just put some limit on it even if it's relatively arbitrary.
Okay, so we'll see about that in the גמרא. Gemara Now we
get to the issue of what does it mean all women and
starting to define different categories of women. So כל אשה שיש לה
וסת דיה שעתה, kol isha she'yesh lah vest dayah sha'atah, any woman
who has a וסת veset which is a regular period, her moment
is sufficient. Meaning even for הלל Hillel that said, and even for
the חכמים, Chachamim, but certainly for הלל Hillel who says we go
all the way back to the last time, that's by a normal
a normal woman. But let's say it is a woman who has
a fixed period, right she knows she bleeds every 28 days like
clockwork, and this month she bled on day 28 exactly when she
was expecting her period. So even that הלל Hillel would say I
don't have to be concerned that it happened earlier. I mean she
regularly bleeds on this day and she bled on this day, I
can assume that's when it happened and it did not happen earlier.
So that's one easy case to exclude, but as I said, we'll
deal with other cases as well: pregnant women, nursing women, other women
who we might be more lenient because we more know what you
know can more assume what has been happening.
That doesn't deal with the issue of
internal—well—oh, you mean because maybe she knows she's she's bleeding every 28
days but maybe it starts earlier and that's a good question. How
does she know her period if she only fixes her period through
the external observation? That's
an interesting point. I was
assuming—that's
a good point
because why would I assume that she had she had established her
period through an internal check? Meaning once you get to other גמראות
Gemaros we'll find out that a woman has to do an internal
check when she's expecting her period in order to allow her, you
know, in order that she can assume she's טהורה tehorah afterwards, but
what you're really saying is yeah, but that's but that's after she
expected her period. Maybe she— Maybe she really always started a half
day before she thought she started. Okay, I have to let me
think about that. That's a good question. How do we exactly know
that that's when it started? All right, I will see if I
can get I can get back to you on that. All right,
so now גמרא Gemara goes the משנה mishnah goes on והמשמשת בעדים
הרי זה כפקודה וממעטת על יד מעת לעת ועל יד מפקידה לפקידה.
Ve-hameshameshet be-edim harei zeh kefekuda u-mema-etet al yad me-et le-et ve-al yad
mi-pekida le-fekida.
And a woman who has sex with literally עדים, edim, witnesses, but
doesn't mean that, it means with checking. The cloth used to check
is called an עד, ed, a witness, because you check, you do
an internal check and it testifies
to whether you're bleeding or not. So we are going to find
out that in addition to checking twice a day, there was also
a practice, again we'll see if everybody did it and whatever, but
also a practice to check right every time before you have sex
because then you want to make sure you're not a נידה niddah
when you're having sex. This by the way the גמרא Gemara, counterbalances
that with a concern like if you're checking right before you have
sex then everybody's going to be a little bit too anxious before
they have sex. ליבו נוקפו ופורש Libo nokfo u-foresh says the גמרא,
Gemara. focusing on the man, he's going to be overly anxious, "my
gosh, she's checking, maybe she's a נידה," niddah, and then they won't
be having sex. And there's also a very important question about how
relevant is this today. Basically some פוסקים poskim actually, I think the
רמב"ם Rambam if I remember correctly, says that even nowadays you have
to at least, you know, check before having sex or at least
or at least the what? Yeah, whatever. So there's different opinions. Some
say right before, right after, whatever. Some say the first three times
a couple has sex after they get married they have to check
to make sure that the sex isn't bringing on bleeding. But certainly
the way I פוסק pasken is it's a little מחלוקת, machlokes, but
the way I פוסק pasken is like all the ראשונים that say
that this is all when you're already in a world of טומאה
and טהרה taharah and you're doing millions of checks and twice a
day, they're also doing checks before sex. But when that's not the
world and you're not in the world of טומאה and טהרה, taharah,
then this even though there's obviously still the איסור in terms of
sex, this does not apply. Okay, so this is though the reality.
We'll talk about that when we get to the גמרא. Gemara. This
is though the reality it's referring to. So a woman who is
doing this, obviously if she checks before sex she can also use
that to limit the time she had to be חושש choshesh when
she bleeds later. Okay, so she normally checks every morning at 6
AM and at 6 PM. Then they had, you know, sex at
11 PM and then she saw, you know whatever, at 3 AM.
So she doesn't have to be חושש choshesh all the way back
to 6 PM, she only has to be חושש choshesh all the
way back till 11 PM because if you're checking for sex, it
also works, you're determining if you're טמא tamei or טהור, tahor, it
also works for this הלכה halacha to limit the time.
Wouldn't it be after she finished having sex? Wouldn't it be 11
PM? No, wouldn't it be after?
Well she checked before.
Okay, so she was fine. Yes. So it would be after they
had sex then because she already said it happened.
No, it could
have happened during. All right. The only time you know not is
since the last check. Okay. כיצד דיה שעתה? Keitzad dayah sha'atah? Now
what is the case of דיה שעתה? dayah sha'atah? Whether it's according
to שמאי Shammai for all women, whether it's according to הלל Hillel
when a woman has her bleeds at the time of her period,
so she doesn't have to be חושש choshesh before? What would be
the example? היתה יושבת במיטה ועסוקה בטהרות. Hayeta yoshevet be-mita ve-asuka be-taharot.
She was in her bed and she was dealing with טהרות. So
you see it doesn't even mention תרומה. terumah It's assuming that a
pretty widespread for people to be eating חולין בטהרה. chullin be-taharah. And
anyway, you know, you want to give as I said חולין chullin
to your friends the כהנים Kohanim or whatever. So everybody's being concerned
about טהרה. taharah. So there you are, you're making dough or whatever
you're making, sitting in your bed or you know, I don't know,
sifting out rice. Whatever you're doing and it's טהור. tahor. ופירשה וראתה.
U-fersha ve-ra'ata.
She got off her bed and then she saw that there was
a blood spot on her bed, that she actually had had her
period. היא טמאה
והן טהורות. Hi tme'a ve-hen tehorot. So she is טמאה tame'ah and
the טהורות tehorot that she's done she's finished dealing with her food,
right? She put it aside, she got up, and then she said,
"Oh my gosh, I just bled." So even if it's a second
after she put the food down, she can assume that she bled
just this second and that it was not while she was dealing
with that food. Now I have to point out in addition to
Dov's very good question,
why it's not so clear why this works even for the woman
who has a regular period because if the woman—I mean depends when
she's if how regular she is. I mean if she's expecting at
9 AM and she put down the food at 8:50 and then
she got up at 9:00, fine. But if she's expecting sometime this
morning and she put down the food and then she stood up,
so okay, but it could have been when she was handling the
food that's still the period that she's expecting. So you know, there's
also the question of how precise. But this somehow assumes that the
dealing with the food occurred prior to the time she was expecting,
then she stood up and she saw the blood and that had
happened and that was in the period when she was expecting to
get her period. Or according to שמאי, Shammai, it would be in
all cases.
ואף—yes?
Ve-af Maybe you could kind of separate these two things, וסת veset
and דיה שעתה? dayah sha'atah?
Well according to הלל Hillel and חכמים, Chachamim, the only case of
דיה שעתה dayah sha'atah is וסת. veset.
Yeah, but if you could kind of formulate it as I go,
but... דיה
שעתה daya she'ata means that
we're not concerned for what might have occurred before. Right. And you
can apply that to someone who's regular. Right. So she's it's like
the category is maybe not dealing with exactly as you as you're
talking about, you know, the 9 a.m. versus sometime today.
Right.
You're just saying again it's a formalism. Once we want to give
it the leniency, we give it the leniency even in cases where
it doesn't make so much sense. I know, but the funny thing
in cases is that you wouldn't want to do it in a
case when it was the exact, you know, opposite of what made
sense. If she actually was dealing with טהרות during the during the
time when she was expected her period, she would have to have
been dealing with it prior to the time, or else it's like
exactly counter, you know, you know, so I see we have to
assume that that's the case. Okay. אף על פי שאמרו מטמא מעת
לעת, Af al pi she'amru metame m'et l'et, now
even going back to the חכמים, Chakhamim, although they say a woman
has is טמא tameh 24 hours back if she hadn't done a
check to limit that time, then אינה מונה אלא משעה שראתה. einah
moneh ella mishat shera'atah. She only counts her נדה days from the
moment she saw. And this is extremely important because a woman who's
a נדה, right, in the תורה Torah we will get later to
our practice of it, she counts from the day she bleeds, that's
day one, she waits till day seven, let's say she bleeds on
a Sunday, שבת Shabbos is then day seven, and then Saturday night
she goes to the מקוה mikvah she's טהורה. tehorah. She could have
been bleeding the entire time. Okay, seven days including the day she
bled, she's טמאה, tame'ah the night after the seventh she goes to
the מקוה mikvah she's טהורה. tehorah. That's according to the תורה. Now
you have let's say she bled on Sunday and she said oh
but the rabbis say I have to be concerned about things I
might have touched 24 hours back going back to שבת. Shabbos. Well
as long as they're telling me I have to be concerned going
back to שבת, Shabbos, I'm going to assume I bled on שבת,
Shabbos, and then I can go to the מקוה mikvah Friday night,
not Saturday night. They say no no no, that would be a
leniency, then you might have a woman who's really a נדה דאורייתא
niddah de'oraisa going to the מקוה mikvah and it wouldn't count. So
being concerned 24 hours back is just being concerned, it's a ספק.
safek. But in terms of actually beginning the seven days, that's only
from the moment she knows definitely she's a נדה, the day she
actually saw. An ongoing theme in this מסכת is going to be,
you know,
women who are not certain of exactly which day they're in during
their cycle, not you know biological cycle but like הלכתי cycle because
of these questions of when exactly do you start counting and so
on. Okay, so that is obviously a very important point, you only
start the seven days from the day you actually see. Let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
So how does it apply to our case?
What? What do you mean? I mean she's חושש choshesh 24 hours
back, but in terms of determining when you go to the מקוה
mikvah only start counting.
She's dealing with the dough,
so the dough is טמאה, tame'ah? it wasn't a case of דיה
שעתה, daya she'ata, it wasn't a special case. A normal case. מחמיר
machmir both ways. Right. מחמיר machmir both ways, the dough is טמאה
teme'ah. up to 24 hours back, but start counting the seven days
from the day you see.
Now that little thing was just according to שמאי. Shammai. They basically
did all three opinions and then get back to שמאי, Shammai, they
explain a lot about דיה שעתה, daya she'ata, right?
What do you mean? דיה שעתה daya she'ata is a case according
to הלל Hillel of אשה שיש לה וסת. isha sheyesh lah veset.
Okay, so everybody has that case, except for הלל Hillel it's a
special case.
According to הלל Hillel we're כיתא kitah with
the כיתא, kitah, except for דיה, daya, except for, except for אשה
שיש
לה וסת. isha sheyesh lah veset. Even הלל Hillel agrees in that
case. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara מאי טעמא
דשמאי? Mai ta'ama d'Shammai? What's the reason of שמאי Shammai, that says
she is טמאה teme'ah. only at the last minute, only when you
know she's definitely טמאה? teme'ah קסבר העמד אשה על חזקתה. Kasavar ha'amed
isha al chazakata.
So it's a simple rule, you establish the woman on her חזקה,
chazakah, she has a status of being טהורה, tehorah, you assume that
that status remained until the last possible minute. ואשה בחזקת טהרה עומדת,
V'isha bechezkas tahara omedes, she's standing with her status of טהורה. tehorah.
והלל, V'Hillel,
so what would הלל Hillel say back to that? That's a pretty
good point. כי אמר העמד דבר על חזקתו, Ki amar ha'amed davar
al chazakaso, when do you say establish something on its חזקה, chazakah,
on its current status? היכא דלית ליה ריעותא מגופיה. Heicha d'leis lei
re'usa migufei. When there is not a ריעותא re'usa like a something
that throws it into question from the thing itself, from the body.
אבל איתתא, Aval ittata, the woman, let's see what this
means. כיון דמגופא קחזיא, Keevan d'migufa kachazya, since she is seeing from
her very body, לא אמרינן אוקמה אחזקתה. lo amrinan okmah a'chazkata. You
don't say establish it on her חזקה. chazakah. Now what does this
mean? It could mean one of two things. I would say the
easier thing that it could mean, which is maybe not as literal,
is that it's something that's called חזקה העשויה להשתנות. chazakah ha'asuyah lehishtanos.
Okay, which is yeah, you have a חזקה, chazakah, but we know
that this status doesn't remain. We know that this status regularly changes.
That's the nature of, you know, of the biology that a woman
will regularly see, so you can't say oh we assume status quo,
because it's a status that is always, you know, about to change.
That's one way of understanding ריעותא מגופיה. re'usa migufei. There's something intrinsically
that throws it into question from the body itself, meaning that we
know that it will change. Although then it should have said that.
It seems that... It seems a little, that's a little non not
fully literal interpretation of that might be what it means. It seems
like it's saying maybe saying something a little bit different, saying that
if the idea is applying a status quo to the person, and
the person themselves is the person is like is some is the
one that has undergone the status change, will undergo a status change,
has undergone a status change, we now see that she's טמאה. teme'ah
So that sort of raises a difficulty in continuing to apply the
previous status to the person, which is if you say it that
way, what it really means is that now she's in a different
status. You can't say retain that status because now she has a
different status, so to keep the old status and say that that
continued to the last minute is more challenging. Anyway, one or the
other, I would prefer to say, meaning there's so let me just
rephrase that in two simple terms. One is called חזקה עשויה להשתנות.
chazaka asuya lehishtanot. It's harder to say חזקה chazaka when it's in
the process of changing. I think that that's my preferred reading of
this. And the other possibility is, yes, she might have had a
חזקה דמעיקרא chazaka de-me-ikara that she was טהורה. tehora. She might have
had a חזקה chazaka in the past that she was טהורה, tehora,
but she has a חזקה דהשתא, chazaka de-hashta, her status now is
that she's טמאה. teme'ah So in a way, they're competing. Like the
past status is saying, keep on applying me forward and assume it
only happened at the last minute; the current status is saying, but
she's טמאה teme'ah, now, why don't we assume that that happened as
far back until we know otherwise? So they're sort of pushing in
opposite directions. So both the חזקה chazaka itself was changeable or in
the process of changing and her current status is different. Yes, David?
Before you go to the legal logic of the positions, is there
the reason of you have insight into the positions' intent to really
ensure?
So the גמרא Gemara is actually, believe it or not, although it
doesn't do this often, will get to it, not in today's דף,
daf, tomorrow's דף, daf, and talks about concerns about like similar to
concerns I mentioned before, you start having all of these issues, people
are going to refrain from having sex, what about פרו ורבו, peru
u-revu, what about, so actually spells out some sort of broader concerns
that might be informing this. So come back tomorrow. Okay, so
let's take a look now. Okay, so that's one way of הלל
Hillel saying. הלל Hillel saying, "Yeah, but it changes or it's changed
and therefore I'm not too impressed with her previous status quo." So
now the גמרא Gemara says ומה ישנא ממקוה? u-mai shna mi-mikveh? How
is this any different than a מקוה? mikveh? What does that mean?
I will talk a minute after we read the comparison about the
very nature of the comparison. דתנן, De-tenan, מקוה שנמדד ונמצא חסר, mikveh
she-nimdad ve-nimtza chaser, if a מקוה mikveh was measured and found lacking,
כל טהרות שנעשו על גביו למפרע בין ברשות הרבים בין ברשות היחיד
טמאות. kol teharot she-na'asu al gabav le-mafrea bein bi-reshut ha-rabim bein bi-reshut
ha-yachid teme'ot. So here's the story: You had a מקוה, mikveh, people
have been using it for the last week, last time you sort
of checked that it was up to water level or the 40
סאה se'ah level was last week. People have been using it. Now
it's now you check it again and you realize, oh my gosh,
it dropped below the level. And the last time we checked it
was a week ago. So what do we have to assume about
everybody that dunked in there for the last week or that used
their dunked their כלים kelim in there for the last week? Maybe
they're still טמאות. teme'ot. So the הלכה halacha is, what do we
say? כל טהרות שנעשו על גביו למפרע, kol teharot she-na'asu al gabav
le-mafrea, retroactively since the last time it was checked, בין ברשות הרבים
ובין ברשות היחיד, bein bi-reshut ha-rabim u-vein bi-reshut ha-yachid, whether in a
private or public domain—I'll talk about that in a minute—טמאות, teme'ot, are
טמאות. teme'ot. You have to assume that they are still טמא. tamei.
So here it seems like you have a מקוה mikveh that is
now, it was good last week, it's not good now, we assume
we take the bad status, the not good now, and apply it
backwards.
And everything is טמא. tamei. So that seems to weigh like הלל.
Hillel. We say she's טמאה teme'ah. now, we'll assume she's טמאה temeah
in the past. And not only that, the גמרא Gemara is going
to say it's even more extreme than הלל, Hillel, because הלל Hillel
just said, I mean it wasn't explicit, but where we know from
other sources and we'll see coming up, that she's only טמאה מספק.
teme'ah mi-safek. This says טמאות teme'ot categorically, that everything in the past
is definitely טמא. tamei. So why, how is this case different from
that case? Now let me say something about רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim
and רשות היחיד, reshut ha-yachid, which I'm we'll get to at the
bottom or tomorrow, I don't want to get into now, but just
so you understand what that phrase is doing. There is principles that
when you have certain doubts of טומאה וטהרה, it matters whether it
applies, it occurs in a רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim or רשות היחיד.
reshut ha-yachid. Why? So this is again a very a very like
unexpected
application analogy. The תורה says that when a woman is suspected of
committing adultery, a סוטה, Sotah, it says ונטמאה, ve-nitma'ah, she became טמאה,
temeah.
defiled. And actually I was just happened the other day that my
son asked me, he said, "What does, I have two words I
want to know what they mean and like are they related: bigotry
and adultery?" So I said they're not related. But then it got
into like an interesting discuss like where does adultery come from? Doesn't
it come from adult? So I actually looked it up and the
Greek word adulter, like adulterate, actually means to defile. So it's actually
interesting like טמאה. temeah So anyway, because of that, now a woman
is suspected as a סוטה Sotah when after her husband... says, you
know, gets jealous and don't go be with this man or whatever,
she goes with the man in private. So private is a רשות
היחיד, reshut hayachid, actually it's being abstracted to that idea, a private
domain as opposed to a public domain. So that's the circumstances of
a סוטה. Sotah. So what we learn from that and what's the
הלכה halacha of a סוטה? Sotah? That she's considered טמאה temeah and
forbidden to her husband after as of that event until you go
through the סוטה Sotah process, right? Bringing to the בית המקדש and
so on. So from there we learn that if there was a
doubt of טומאה, we apply this completely like abstracted to a world
of טומאה and טהרה, taharah, nothing to do with the realities of
the circumstances there and so on. If there's a doubt of טומאה
in a private domain, we assume it's טמאה. temeah And if there's
a doubt of טומאה in a public domain, we assume it is
טהורה. tehorah. Okay, so that is, we'll get more to that tomorrow,
but that is again, obviously there's like a million questions you can
ask about about the whole application and abstraction. But that's the point
that this is making is that this does not apply here. The
normal ways of thinking about private and public domain are not relevant
for this מקוה mikvah case, because in this מקוה mikvah case we
assume it's definitely טמאה temeah, and it doesn't even get into those
public and private domain questions. Okay, so that's what that phrase is
doing. I should tell you by the way that this huge תוספות
Tosafot in the beginning says, why don't we discuss the private-public domain
issue by the נדה? Right? Why do we just discuss it by
these other cases? And he has like a lot of answers. Maybe
it doesn't apply retroactively, maybe this, maybe that. But I would suggest
again the question of, do we say this when, you know, a
נדה which is an intersection of classic טומאה and טהרה taharah and
the issue of the forbidden, you know, the איסור עריות issur arayot
and the idea of the forbidden sex and how does that category,
what type of category do you put that in, you know, is
an important question. So we don't discuss the private-public domain by נדה,
why is that? Maybe it's because it's somewhat of a hybrid category.
Okay, but I just to know, I won't give you the answers,
that's not the answer תוספות Tosafot gives. תוספות Tosafot has that long
discussion. So let's put that aside, private-public domain. What we see is
the מקוה mikvah is, you treat, now it's חסר, chaser, you say
retroactively definitely טמא. tameh. So how is that different than the נדה?
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. And then I'll say
another word about the comparison. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
לשמאי קשיא למפרע. leShammai kashya lemafre'a. For שמאי, Shammai, that whole thing,
the whole fact that retroactively she's טמאה temeah, is difficult. It goes
against, for the woman he says it's only from this moment on.
להלל קשיא ודאי. leHillel kashya vaday. For הלל, Hillel, it's questionable because
it sounds like it's definitely טמאה temeah, retroactively by the מקוה mikvah
case. ואילו מעת לעת שבנדה, ve'ilu me'et le'et shebeNiddah, when we say
24 hours backwards of a נדה that you're concerned, תולין, tolin, it
means that we suspend.
We don't we're not it's possibly טמאה, not definitely. לא אוכלין ולא
שורפין. lo ochlin velo sorfin. You don't eat the food if it's
תרומה terumah that was touched, you don't eat it because maybe it's
תרומה טמאה, trumah temeah, but you don't burn it because maybe it's
טהור. tahor. You let it rot. You let it decompose. Okay, so
that's what you do. So it's and now that wasn't in our
משנה Mishna but we know that from other sources. We'll see it
later. So that's a doubt in our משנה Mishna, retroactive. How come
by the מקוה mikvah it's definitely
טמא? tameh? ואילו הכא בטומאה ודאי, ve'ilu hacha betumah vaday, and here
it sounds like by the מקוה mikvah case it's definitely טמא. tameh.
So this case of the מקוה mikvah is clearly worse, both according
to הלל Hillel and שמאי. Shammai How is that possible or why
is that? The answer the גמרא Gemara says, well okay, the גמרא
Gemara says, התם, hatam, no, here's the reason. משום דאיכא למימר העמד
טמא על חזקתו ואימא לא טבל. mishum de'ika lemeimar ha'amed tameh al
chezkato ve'eima lo taval. No, because remember, the whole thing is figuring
out what the status is. The מקוה mikvah might have had a
status of being a שלם, shalem, of being כשר. kosher. But something
else had a status of being no good. What was it? The
person or the כלי kli that you're dunking in the מקוה. mikvah.
That started as טמא. tameh. You're coming to try to change the
status. You want to change the status, you have to prove that
you successfully changed the status. You want to make it from טמא
tameh to טהור. tahor. So any doubt about the מקוה mikvah is
not going to be enough to override the status of the person
or the כלי kli that was טמא. tameh. As opposed to the
woman who starts off being טהורה. tehorah. Maybe there we should say
if you want to say she's טמאה, you have to prove that
that that happened. So let's take a look. But so that seems
very clear. The גמרא Gemara goes back and forth about this in
the next few lines, but in the end it reverts to this.
So let's take a look.
משום דאיכא למימר העמד טמא על חזקתו ואימא לא טבל. mishum de'ika
lemeimar ha'amed tameh al chezkato ve'eima lo taval. Maybe you didn't go
into the מקוה. mikvah. Maybe it wasn't a כשר מקוה. kosher mikvah.
ואיכא דאמרי אדרבה העמד מקוה על חזקתו ואימא לא חסר. ve'ika de'amrei
adaraba ha'amed mikvah al chezkato ve'eima lo chaser. Okay, but opposite that
you have a מקוה mikvah that had a status of being כשר.
kosher. So we should say let's give that its status quo. Okay,
but they're competing. הרי חסר לפניך. harei chaser lefanecha. Oh, no, you
can't just say assume the מקוה mikvah was שלם. shalem. We now
have evidence that it's not good, it's under the line. So that
throws it into doubt. So the גמרא Gemara says... So basically you
understand how it's setting up? Makes a lot of sense. The מקוה
mikvah had a חזקה chazakah of being כשר. kosher. But now it's
חסר. chaseir. So that is like the case of the woman who,
and you're trying to figure out, how does the previous status and
the current status, what does it do to the period in between?
You could go either way. But at but what the גמרא Gemara
is saying is at least it's enough of a doubt that it's
not sufficient to change the כלי kli or the person that was
טמא tamei that went into the מקוה mikveh because these things are
competing. Okay, so that's why the כלי kli or the person remains
definitely טמא tamei because there's at least some question about this period
in between. So now the and seems that that's clearly different than
the נדה case, but the גמרא Gemara still wants to articulate this.
So let's take a look.
Different than the נדה case, but it's not נדה, it's the
same thing as the touch. No,
those things also had a חזקת טהרה, chezkat taharah, right? So where
so right? Okay. So the so the גמרא Gemara says, הכא נמי
הרי דם לפניך, hacha nami harei dam lefanecha, how about the נדה?
Right now she she actually is טמאה, there's blood. So השתא הוא
דחזאי. hashta hu dechazai.
Not necessarily, maybe she just bled now. That doesn't mean she bled
before. הכא נמי השתא הוא דחסר, hacha nami hashta hu dechaseir, so
by the מקוה, mikveh, same, maybe it just got lacking now. So
you know, but of course so now it finally gets back to
the major distinguishing point. הכי השתא? hechi hashta? How do you make
the comparison? התם איכא למימר חסר ואתי חסר ואתי. hatam ika lemeimar
chaseir ve-atei chaseir ve-atei. הכא מיכא למימר חזי ואתי חזי ואתי. hacha
mika lemeimar chazai ve-atei chazai ve-atei.
Excuse me, it's not yet back to the obvious distinction of חזקת
טומאה, chezkat tumah, it makes another difference which goes back to the
idea of מגופא migufa or possibly what that meant. It says there's
a reality by a מקוה. mikveh. A מקוה, mikveh, every time you
use it, a little water goes out. Okay. So a מקוה mikveh
is always on the process of getting less and less and less,
so therefore that makes its whole idea of status quo very questionable.
A woman is not constantly in the process of bleeding a little
little bit until it finally comes out. Okay. So therefore again, beside
before getting to the obvious difference that I've already put out there,
which it will get back to, which is that you had a
something טמא tamei that you have to try to change the status,
ignoring the טמא tamei person, just looking at the מקוה mikveh starting
שלם shaleim and is now חסר, chaseir, the woman who was טהור
tahor and now has bled, it says there's still a stronger status
quo for the woman because the מקוה's mikveh always in the process
of losing water. Yes.
But the מקוה's mikveh losing a little water, a little water, but
there's a point right above that
it's fine and below that it's no longer כשר. kasher. Right. But
that is an objective point. Right. It might be a מחלוקת machlokes
what that is, but it is an objective point. Right. So this
this is really unusual idea that it's because at any point the
מקוה mikveh is either כשר kasher or is not.
Right. But what the גמרא Gemara is saying is I already told
you there is a concept called חזקה העשויה להשתנות. chazakah ha-asuyah lish-tanos.
A חזקה chazakah status quo that its nature is it's going to
change, so it's not like a stat- a fixed status quo. So
this is even worse than עשויה להשתנות. asuyah lish-tanos. This is a
חזקה chazakah that's always in the process of about of changing, right?
It's always working against itself.
So or that at any point this מקוה mikveh may become not-
exactly.
So the גמרא Gemara so now the גמרא Gemara has an interesting
sort of biological discussion and it'll always be interesting when the גמרא
Gemara sort of gets to biological issues. And so the גמרא Gemara
says, okay, הכא מיכא למימר חזי ואתי חזי ואתי, hacha mika lemeimar
chazai ve-atei chazai ve-atei, who can you can you say she's like
a little bit seeing seeing seeing until she sees enough? No, it's
not the same reality. גמרא Gemara says, ומאי קושיא? umai kushia? Why
is that difficult? Why is it not the same type of reality?
דילמא הגס הגס חזיתיה. dilma hagas hagas chaziteih. Maybe she sort of
it slowly grew, she saw after it slowly increased. What does this
mean? Actually this actually does is sort of reflect the bio- does
reflect the biological reality, right? Because what I mean, well Sally will
help me out here, but the uterine lining continues to develop. Now
does it develop at the time does it remain stable before it
sloughs off at the period or is it always increasing, the uterine
lining? Increasing?
I meaning like the amount, yeah, the amount of lining, the the
the blood, you know, the blood vessels and so on, or no
it's sort of is stable after a or pretty much grows till
the and then it starts sloughs off?
I mean the way it's drawn is a slope. Right, right. And
then it's a plateau.
And then it's a plateau.
But I don't know when- right.
So anyway, the גמרא Gemara sort of is saying that the blood
is constantly increasing till finally it comes out. Now that doesn't mean
the גמרא Gemara really understood the whole, you know, uterine lining and
so on. The גמרא Gemara actually Rabbi Love from the Yeshiva once
said that it sounds like the גמרא's Gemara idea of the uterus
and the blood was sort of like a soap dispenser.
Like there's a lot of blood there and like you push it
and like the blood comes out or like eventually the blood gets
to be enough so some blood drips out. But that seems to
be the idea. So the גמרא's Gemara saying well what do you
mean? A woman also, the blood is increasing until finally it starts
coming out. So it's always in the process of, as it were,
undermining her
חזקה chazakah because it's constantly
So if that's true, what is the difference? Why by the מקווה
*mikvah* do we say it's definitely a problem and the woman, it's
a ספק safek? *safek* according to שמאי Shammai *Shammai* it isn't? So
now it finally goes back to what it said before, which is,
you know, which is the most obvious. גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says התם
איכא תרתי לריעותא הכא איכא hasam ika tarti l'reiusa hacha ika. חדא
לריעותא *hatam ika tarti lerei'usa hacha ika chada lerei'usa*. There, there are
two things wrong by the מקווה *mikvah*. Here, there's only one thing
wrong. What are the one thing wrong? The one thing wrong is
she's now, you know, טמאה *temei'ah*. What are the two things wrong
by the מקווה *mikvah*? Number one, the מקווה *mikvah* is now חסר
*chaser*. And number two, you start with something that is already טמא
tamei *tamei*. So you're trying to change the status of the other
thing. So really, it's funny that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sort of
went to this whole discussion, but it did help clarify the sort
of conceptually what's going on. And conceptually, it's very clear. You have
a previous חזקה chazaka *chazakah*, you have a current different status. What
does that do to the period in between? This חזקה chazaka *chazakah*
is weaker than a normal חזקה chazaka. *chazakah*, and this might explain
הלל *Hillel*, because it's in the process of changing. Okay, so that
sort of throws this period in the middle into ספק safek? *safek*.
And, but what would certainly not work if you've got a person
טמא tamei, *tamei* going into the מקווה *mikvah* and it's got these
question marks on it, you can't change his status unless you can
prove the מקווה *mikvah* was good. That's that case. Whereas in the
case by the נידה *niddah*, it remains somewhat of a question, so
שמאי *Shammai* says she's okay and הלל *Hillel* says that she is
טמאה מספק misafek. *temei'ah mi'safek*. So it's a very nice way of
conceptually presenting it. And I did want to say something about the
comparison to the מקווה *mikvah* because there's a fascinating book out there
on נידה *niddah*, like more מסכת נידה *Masechet Niddah*, but the parts
of it that are mostly the parts of it that are relevant
today, by
a female scholar by the name of Charlotte Fonrobert. It's called Menstrual
Purity, or it might be Impurity, but I think it's Purity because
I thought that was a better title than Impurity. Anyway, and she
has like these, she focuses on certain themes that go on here
and sort of, you know, some like, you know, other issues that
are going on. So anyway, the one big issue which we will
constantly be revisiting, you know, is the way in which the woman
sort of gets objectified in the process. She gets talked of as
an object and analyzed by הלכה *halacha* and by the rabbis. Now
of course, as she points out, this is what הלכה *halacha* does
to everything. Everything gets objectified, right? I actually recently wrote, I actually
recently wrote a whole פרשה *parsha* sheet by the מצורע *metzora*, you
know, about how doctors have to objectify their patients in order to
deal with it dispassionately. But of course, that depersonalizes. So if we
were learning מסכת זבים *Masechet Zavim*, we would talk about depersonalizing the
male זב *zav*. But fine, it's not, nobody's picking on the woman
נידה *niddah*, but that still is the reality of the halachic system.
So she sort of said, you know, here, the very first דף
daf. *daf*, you have the, you know, the bleeding woman compared to
the leaky מקווה *mikvah*. You know, so,
which was a pretty, pretty colorful way of saying it. But anyway,
and what's nice about this book, I should say, is that it's
not like, you know, like angry or critical. It's just, you know,
I mean it's critical in terms of scholarly critical, but it just,
you know, points out the way these things function in the halachic
system. And that definitely will come up, you know, this issue about
sort
of, about sort of seeing the woman here as a halachic object
trying to determine the status.
Yes. I teach medical students to objectify people all the time.
There you go.
Today I'm going to be objectifying men on prostate cancer.
Right. So, you know, and הלכה *halacha* does it, right, all the
time, but, you know, but it, so it's not, again, like the
women are being picked on here, but it still is a reality
of what's going on.
But there are no women in this. They're not asking women, they're
not calling women in to say.
Right. And we will see there are a few times where women's
voices come up about their realities and it's interesting how much they're
given credence or not. So that's definitely going to be an interesting
question. Right. Absolutely. And it comes up in הלכה *halacha* as well
in a number of things that the פוסקים *poskim* actually say we
asked women about this and so on. So this is a fascinating
area where the rabbis have to פסקן *pasken* about things that are
completely out of their alien, alien, right, immediate knowledge.
The image of the bleeding woman and the מקווה *mikvah*. Yes, they
both become טמא tamei, *tamei* when the liquid starts.
Right. Well, that's obviously the comparison is the liquid slowly departing. The
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* right here, מקווה *mikvah* slowly leaking, right? So okay.
But it's not going to be, then, ספק safek. טמא tamei. *safek
tamei*. It's only for
תרומה terumah *terumah* and קדשים *kodshim*.
Yeah. I mean, you get מלקות *malkos*, you know, how, whatever, but
yes, right. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* goes on. ומאי
שנא *u'mai shna*, so one case was the מקווה *mikvah* comparison, and
that had to do with the fact that the person started with
a חזקת טומאה *chezkat tumah*. And now we're going to look at
one other comparison, which is מאי שנא מחבית *mai shna me'chavis*, from
the barrel. Actually, here there's liquids as well, a barrel filled with
wine. דתנן *de'tnan*, היה בודק את החבית להיות מפריש עליה תרומה terumah.
והולך *haya bodek et hachavis l'hiyot mafrish aleha terumah v'holech*. So you
check, you have a barrel filled with wine, and you're going to
use this as your תרומה terumah as your תרומה terumah. barrel. So
every time you take תרומה terumah on your wine, you have to
take תרומה terumah on your wine, you're going to say, oh, it's
in another another like one ounce of in that barrel is my
תרומה. Another one ounce of that barrel until you do a thousand
because it has a thousand ounces and then you'll give the whole
barrel to the כהן. kohen. So this is going to be your
תרומה barrel and you're constantly going to be designating wine in it
for your תרומה. Okay, so you were you checked it to make
sure the wine was good and והוא מפריש עליה תרומה והולך v'hu
mafrish aleha terumah v'holech that you would on an ongoing process designate
תרומה in the barrel. ואחר כך נמצא חומץ. v'acharkach nimtza chometz. And
then, when you went to check it one day, you found out
that it had turned into vinegar. And now, if it whenever it
was vinegar, your תרומה wouldn't have worked. Why? A, there's a debate
in the גמרא Gemara whether vinegar and wine is considered one מין,
min, one type of a thing, you know, or two, and if
it's two you can't take from one מין min on another, from
apples onto pears. And תוספות Tosfos says even if normally they're one
מין min and it does work, that's only if you wanted to
do חומץ chometz onto wine, but if you wanted to do wine
on wine and it turned out to be חומץ, chometz, then it's
תרומה בטעות. terumah b'taos. Okay, so here the question is when did
it turn into vinegar? It started with wine, now it's vinegar, when
did that happen? Okay, and I guess presumably wine is constantly in
the process of, right, because becoming turning into vinegar. So so it
says where are we? כל ג' ימים ודאי. kol gimmel yamim vaday.
The first three days definite. I'm taking out the parentheses I'll say
why in a minute. מכאן ואילך ספק. mikan v'eilach safek. That point
after it's a doubt. Now there's a מחלוקת machlokes where this appears
in the גמרא Gemara about what three days are definite. Right, you
could go either way. The first three days after you checked were
definitely good, after that it's all in doubt. Or the first three
days backwards are definitely bad, and before that it's all in doubt.
But either way, you're having a whole major period that's in doubt
in the middle. All right, so how is that different than שמאי,
according to שמאי, than the case of the woman? Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says קשיא לשמאי, kasha l'Shammai, it's difficult according to שמאי,
because here you retroactively it's it's you assume no good מספק. So
the גמרא Gemara says התם משום דאיכא למימר העמד טבל על חזקתו
ואימא לא ניתקן. hasam mishum d'ika l'meimar amed tevel al chazkaso v'eimar
lo nitken. Ah, it's very similar to the מקוה mikvah case. With
the מקוה mikvah we had a טמא tamei. person who we had
a defi- who we had to have something definitely good to change
his status. Here we have wine, other wine, that I was taking,
you know, out in the field or whatever, that's definitely טבל. tevel.
And I need this wine to be good to change that bad
status of טבל tevel over there. Okay, so it's the same point.
Yes, everybody agrees that the forward going חזקה chazaka should say good,
the backward חזקה chazaka should say bad, it raises questions. שמאי would
say normally I'll say you're okay, but if you want to say
use this to change the status of something else, no, there's too
much of a doubt here that the very fact that it's thrown
into doubt it does raise you know you can't change a bad
status. You can't make the person טהור tahor with a מקוה mikvah
that has this doubt, you can't make טבל tevel tahor- you know
kosher with a wine that has this doubt, but if it's just
about the wine itself or in this case the woman herself, I'll
say she's טהורה. tehora. Because she actually has her חזקת טהרה. chazkas
tahara. That's what שמאי would say. אדרבה aderaba says the גמרא, Gemara
now it's going to go back and forth again and just come
back to where it to what it said. העמד יין על חזקתו
ואימא לא החמיץ. ha'med yayin al chazkaso v'eimar lo hachmitz. Why don't
we say the wine retains its status and it didn't become vinegar?
No, that's counteracted. הרי החמיץ לפניך. harei hachmitz lefanecha. You see it
became vinegar. הכא נמי הרי דם לפניך. hacha nami harei dam lefanecha.
So here too she's already bled. Again, it's going back and forth
to deal with this you know ignoring the difference that there's a
person out- you know whatever, a טבל tevel outside. So the גמרא
says הכא נמי הרי דם לפניך. No, השתא הוא דחזאי. No, maybe
now is when she she just saw now so that's why we
can assume it. התם נמי השתא הוא דהחמיץ. hasam nami hashta hu
d'hachmitz. By the wine also say now it became vinegar. השתא? השתא?
hashta? hashta? One minute, how can you compare her? התם איכא למימר
החמיץ ואתא החמיץ ואתא. hasam ika l'meimar hachmitz v'asa hachmitz v'asa. Right,
you see this is very- completely parallel. Uh, there the wine is
constantly is slowly in a process of becoming vinegar. הכא מי איכא
למימר חזאי ואתי חזאי ואתי. hacha mi ika l'meimar hazai v'asi hazai
v'asi. Here can you say that a woman is slowly in the
process of bleeding? So that makes the woman case better, stronger her
חזקה. גמרא says ומאי קשיא? u'mai kasha? Why is it difficult? דילמא
הגס הגס חזיא. dilma hagas hagas hazai. Maybe it slowly grows and
then she sees the am- the wine, you see I did it-
the blood. So basically the גמרא set it up again. It's an
exact comparison. A חזקה of being good, the wine, the woman, a
reality of having changed to the non-desired status, vinegar and having bled,
and this original חזקה is in the process of changing. Slowly getting
you know slowly turning into vinegar, slowly in the process of menstruating
of getting to the point where she actually bleeds. So what makes
the wine case worse? And now we go back to what we
said before because there's טבל. tevel. So the גמרא says התם איכא
תרתי לריעותא הכא איכא. Yeah, so
here there's only one problem, the woman's status and do we do
in this in-between stage. There, in addition to the question of the
status of the wine, you have to change the status of the
טבל. tevel. The טבל tevel is definitely no good. So it's exactly
parallel. When these things are competing and this thing is a question,
you might say taking the thing by itself it's okay, it has
a חזקת טהרה, chazakas tahara, but that doesn't mean you're going to
say it's enough to change the status of something else, the definite
status: טמא, טבל, tevel, and so on. Okay, so that was how
we nicely conceptualize what's going on here and how it's different from
the other case. Let's just read till the end of the דף.
So the גמרא says like this: ורמי חבית אמיקווה. u'rami chavis a'mikvah.
One minute, okay, that was all very nice, but now the barrel
case doesn't work with the מקוה mikvah case, because those are, right,
we compared everything to the woman, now let's compare those two to
one another. מאי שנא הכא ודאי ומאי שנא הכא ספק? mai shna
hacha vadai u'mai shna hacha safek?
By the מקוה, mikvah, we said the person was ודאי vadai טמא,
right? He went into a questionable מקוה, mikvah, he's ודאי vadai טמא.
So by the טבל tevel and the wine, why don't we say
it's ודאי? vadai? Excuse me, why did we say ספק? safek. It
should be ודאי, vadai, right, if we're going to make that comparison.
אמר רבי חנינא מסורא: Amar Rabbi Chanina mi-Sura: מאן תנא חבית Man
tanna chavis רבי שמעון היא. Rabbi Shimon hi.
Who is the one, the author of that משנה by חבית chavis
that says ספק? safek? It was רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. דלגבי מקוה
נמי ספק משוי לה. de-legabei mikvah nami safek meshavei lah. And רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon by the מקוה mikvah case would also say ספק.
safek How do you know? דתניא, de-tanya, we taught it in a
משנה, I think it's דתניא de-tanyan or דתניא. de-tanya. דתניא: De-tanya: מקוה
שנמדד ונמצא חסר, mikvah shenimdad ve'nimtza chaser,
our case of a מקוה mikvah that was measured and found to
be lacking, כל הטהרות שנעשו על גביו למפרע, kol ha-tehoros shena'asu al
gabav lemafrea, everything that was done, dunked in it retroactively, כלים, kelim,
people, בין ברשות הרבים בין ברשות היחיד, bein b'reshus harabbim bein b'reshus
hayachid, whether public or private, טמאות temei'os are ודאי vadai טמא. רבי
שמעון אומר: Rabbi Shimon omer: ברשות הרבים טהורות, b'reshus harabbim tehoros, ברשות
היחיד תולין. b'reshus hayachid tolin.
He says it's a ספק. safek So what do you do by
a ספק? safek Number one, ספק safek in רשות הרבים reshus harabbim
we say טהור tahor based on the סוטה sotah comparison. And רשות
היחיד, reshus hayachid, now you should say ודאי, vadai, why he says
תולין, tolin, ספק safek as opposed to ודאי, vadai, is not so
clear, we'll continue to discuss that tomorrow. But basically what do you
have? In those two cases of competing חזקות, chazakas, questionable middle state,
what does it do if you want to change something else's state?
The guy dunking in the מקוה, mikvah, the טבל tevel becoming becoming
okay. So according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, it's ספק changes the
טבל, tevel, ספק changes the things that were dunked. And according to
the חכמים, chachamim, it's ודאי vadai does not. Since this is a
question and that had a ודאי vadai status, those things retain their
ודאי vadai status of no good, but for רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
it's enough to create a ספק in that. We'll continue to look
at that tomorrow. Right, okay, that's a מציאות metzius question. Okay, continue
tomorrow.